A Guide to the Gibson Family Papers, 1775-1938
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Gibson family Papers, 1775-1938
Library of Virginia
25342
1.35 cubic feet (3 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. J. Hampden Chamberlayne, 1 June 1961.
Biographical/Historical Information
Patrick Gibson (d. 1827), the son of George Gibson (d. 1821), of Petersburg and Richmond, Virginia, was an exporter of cotton and tobacco. He married Elizabeth Sanderson (d. 1811) in 1797 and they had seven children: George Hardy (1797-1798), Josephine Eleanor (1799-1802), George Sanderson (1800-1872), Henry (1802-1843), Mary Elizabeth (1805-1875), Alexander (1808-1872) and Patrick (1809-1868).
In 1813, Patrick married Martha Ann Elizabeth Macmurdo (1792-1867). Martha was the daughter of Charles James Macmurdo (b. 1771) and Elizabeth Selden (1770-1792) of Richmond, Virginia. Martha and Patrick had seven children including Ann Elizabeth (b. 1817) and Churchill Jones (1819-1892). Ann Elizabeth Gibson married Reverend Hobart Bartlett in 1839 and George Gibson in 1856. Charles Jones Gibson attended Bristol College (Pa.), served as a minister in Petersburg, Virginia, and was married to Lucy Fitz Hugh Atkinson.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1775-1938, including booklets, correspondence, genealogy, newsclippings, ephemera, and financial materials of the Gibson family of Petersburg and Richmond, Virginia. The bulk of the collection consists of family correspondence. The major correspondents are: Patrick Gibson; his wife, Martha Ann Elizabeth Macmurdo Gibson; two of their children, Ann Elizabeth "Bess" Jones Gibson and Churchill Jones Gibson; a cousin, Robert Fitzgerald; Charles James Macmurdo, Churchill Jones and his wife, Martha Selden Jones.
Topics covered in the correspondence pertain to financial affairs, marriages, health, births, deaths, social events, travel, and the education of the children. Of note, are letters from former slaves of Martha Macmurdo Gibson's; correspondence from Patrick Gibson, dated 23 June 1807, concerning the trial of Aaron Burr in Richmond, Virginia; and correspondence regarding secession and the Civil War. Also of note are two lengthy letters from Jubal Early to William Mahone, dated 1871, regarding an article in which negative comments were made about Early, Robert E. Lee, and other Confederate generals, by Mahone. Early's rebuttal letters to Mahone contain very detailed information on several Civil War battles, including Bristoe Station (Va.) and Spotsylvania Court House (Va.).
Also included in the collection are compositions written by Martha Ann Elizabeth Macmurdo Gibson, 1806-1808; military papers of John Hampden Chamberlayne, 1903-1919; poems by John A. Blair, 1809-1813; free negro certificates, 1851-1861; recipes and medicinal cures, 1821-1886. The collection also contains some genealogical information on the Gibson and Macmurdo families, as well as correspondence from 1889 concerning genealogy of the Starke family of Petersburg and Staunton, Virginia.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Oversized folder located in oversize, box 101.
Contents List
- Booklets, 1827-1871 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Business cards, nd (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Compositions, 1806-1808 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Confederate currency, 1861-1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1775-1799 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1802-1809 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1810-1812 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1815-1816 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1817-1818 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1819-1821 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1823-1829 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1830-1833 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1835-1836 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1837-1838 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1839-1842 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1843-1849 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1850-1854 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1855-1859 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1860-1862 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1863-1864 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1865-1889 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1890-1919 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, Churchill Gibson, outgoing to, Ann E. Gibson, nd (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, Martha A.E. Gibson, incoming from, Ann E. Gibson, nd (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, Martha A.E. Gibson, incoming from, Churchill Gibson, nd (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, Martha A.E. Gibson, incoming from, Patrick Gibson, nd (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Martha A.E. Gibson, incoming from, miscellaneous, nd (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Martha A.E. Gibson, outgoing to, Ann E. Gibson, nd (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Martha A.E. Gibson, outgoing to, Patrick Gibson, nd (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Martha A.E. Gibson, outgoing to Martha Jones, nd (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Gibson-Macmurdo family, nd (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Ephemera, 1792-1892 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Ephemera, nd (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Financial records, 1859-1862 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Free negro certificates, 1851-1861 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Genealogy, nd (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Inventory notecards, nd (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Magazines, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Military papers, 1903-1919 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Miscellaneous, 1822-1919 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Newsclippings, 1884-1912 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Poems, 1809-1813 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Recipes and medical remedies, 1821-1886 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Miscellaneous, 1858-1917 (Box Oversize, Folder 1)